A Guide to the Victor V. Martin Autograph Collection 1694-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Victor V. Martin Autograph Collection 1694-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11315
There are thirteen items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Paul K. Walker on behalf of the United States Army Corps of Engineers, Office of History, Humphrey's Engineer Center, Alexandria, Virginia, on June 14, 1997. There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Martin was special counsel for forty-one years in the office of the Army Chief of Engineers. He was a major in the Army Reserve, and a member of the American Military Engineers, the Sons of the American Revolution, the Fossils Club, and the Anteaters Club. He was a native of Alma, Kansas and was married to Wilhemina Hietmuller. Martin died in Washington, D. C. on May 11, 1962.
Scope and Content Information
This fine collection of autographs, compiled by Victor V. Martin, consists of thirteen items, 1694-1945, of correspondence and documents bearing the signatures of a variety of famous persons.
Victor V. Martin compiled a collection of original letters and documents containing autographs of United States presidents as well as kings, persons of nobility, statesmen, and other famous persons. The letters and manuscripts are organized in alphabetical order by the writer.
Contents List
- Item, 1795 Jul 29; 1 p. (Box 1)
  ANS: William Henry Harrison, Headquarters, Greeneville, [Tennessee], to Col. Meiggs.
- Item, 1824 Jan 10; 1p. (Box 1)
  AMsS: Thomas Jefferson, "Monticello," Albemarle County, Virginia, to Thomas Jefferson Grotjan. [Writes at the request of the recipient's mother a memento which might have a favorable influence on the course of his life. Advises on the positive feelings and actions one should have toward God, one's parents, one's neighbor, and one's country, and further advises him to be just and true.]
  Andrew Jackson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Thomas Jefferson Grotjan. [Several years later, Mr. Grotjan requests Andrew Jackson to add to Thomas Jefferson's document a statement which would also serve as an inspiration to their son. He commends on the "admirable advice given to his son by that virtuous patriot and enlightened statesman" and recommends following that advice which contains the "purest morality" and "noblest sentiments."]
- Item, 1834 Nov 18; 1 p. (Box 1)
  ALS: Frances Scott Key, Geo[rge] Town, to Hagner, Gratist & Thornton. [Requests a meeting of their board to discuss compliance under the resolution of Congress to award on the claims of Farrow and Harris.]
- Item, 1777 Dec 27; 2 p. on 1 l. w/address leaf (Box 1)
  ALS: Marquis de Lafayette, "at camp," to Lieutenant Jonathan [Ford] Moriss [sic], [Fourth] Con[tinental] Artillerists. at Morisstown [sic], [New Jersey]. [Expresses concern that Major [Joseph] Moriss [sic] went down from the camp to Morisstown [sic] without a surgeon in attendance. Offers a good French surgeon belonging to Count de Pulaski as well as a personal servant to take care of the major.]
- Item, 1792 Oct 17; 1 p. (Box 1)
  ALS: Tobias Lear, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Col. Samuel Hodgdon. [Writes as secretary to George Washington, president of the United States. Informs him, on behalf of the president, that considering the situation on the frontier of Carolina and the fact that arms cannot immediately be procured for that state, that the colonel has permission to furnish six hundred stand of arms out of the public stores under his care.]
- Item, 1865 Feb 8; 1 p. (Box 1)
  ANS: Abraham Lincoln quote and photograph. ["Let these men take the oath of Dec. 8, 1863 & be discharged ALincoln Feb. 8, 1865" concerning his Proclamation of Amnesty and Reconstruction which offered pardon to Confederates who took a loyalty oath. Note placed below an original [Matthew B.] Brady photograph of Lincoln and mounted in a frame.]
- Item, 1797 Feb 22 (Box 1)
  ANS: Charles Martin, Lieutenant, to the Issuing Commissary, Fort LeBoeuf. [Requests one gallon of whiskey for the non-commissioned officers and soldiers under his command to celebrate the president's [George Washington] birthday.]
- Item, 1828 Apr 27; 1 p. (Box 1)
  ALS: Zachary Taylor, Lt. Col. of the U.S. Army, New Orleans, Louisiana, to W[illiam] Lee, Tr[easury] Dep[artmen]t, Washington, D.C. [Concerns the receipt of a draft drawn on the Bank of the United States by the Treasury on account for recruiting service in Louisville, Kentucky between the 15th of March 1824 and the 30th of April 1826.]
- Item, 1945 Nov 21; 1 p. (Box 1)
  TLS: Harry S. Truman, The White House, Washington, D.C., to Victor V. Martin, Ward Department, Washington, D.C. [Sends with pleasure a signed letter to add to Martin's collection of "original letters written by every President from George Washington to Franklin D. Roosevelts."
- Item, 1773 Mar 1 (Oversize OS Box W-2)
  ADS: Lord Fairfax, Baron of Cameron. [Deed granted unto David Ross and Company of the Province of Maryland for a tract of land on the Potomac River in Berkeley County.]
- Item, 1788 Sep 18 (Oversize OS Box W-2)
  DS: John Hancock. [Appointment of John Choate as justice in Essex County, Massachussetts for the term of seven years.]
- Item, 1694 Apr 28; 1 p. (Oversize OS Box W-2)
  Louis XIV, King of France, Versailles, to his son the dauphin, Commander-in-Chief of the Army of Flanders. [Requests that he use Monsieur d'Auvray as a Brigadier General in the Army of Flanders as best suited.]
- Item, 1790 (Oversize OS Box W-2)
  ADS: George Washington and Thomas Jeffeson. [Appointment of Nathaniel Barrett of Massachussetts as Consul of the United States to France.]